<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mshires.net//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mshires.net//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-02-13T02:46:31+00:00</updated><id>https://mshires.net//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Michael Shires</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Doing the Right Thing</title><link href="https://mshires.net//blog/2023/integrity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Doing the Right Thing"/><published>2023-12-20T01:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-20T01:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mshires.net//blog/2023/integrity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mshires.net//blog/2023/integrity/"><![CDATA[<p>“Doing the Right Thing”</p> <p>This was inspired by a series of incentives the nuclear navy has put out to increase retention for its mid-career sailors, around the 6-10 years of service mark (coincidentally where I’m at). I originally wanted to talk about how there seems to be a disconnect between what is actually hurting retention and their efforts. I also wanted to talk about how it feels like a slap in the face to have an organization go back on what was once set in stone policies to give service members pennies on the dollar for what their worth. However, the more I thought about it the more I realized what I wanted to talk about was integrity.</p> <p>Integrity.</p> <p><em>Integrity.</em></p> <p>Once more for effect. The elusive, gold standard of what someone strives for. A pure, indelible shield against the moral quandaries of the world by having <em>integrity</em>. What is integrity? If you asked anyone that’s in the military or been exposed to a morals or ethics class, they’d probably say “doing the right thing even when no one’s looking”. If you dug deeper you could probably get more substantive answers, such as “having the moral courage to take responsibility for one’s actions”, or “Placing loyalty to <em>insert organization</em> over yourself”. I would agree with most of those, but I would also challenge anyone who’s reading this and a leader in some way to think about another question - what does it mean to not have integrity?</p> <p>We all strive to live our lives with integrity, and we’re also told that perfection is never attainable. The nuclear navy has a term called “constructive dissatisfaction” - this idea that we’re never perfect, and we can always improve. It can be a substantial cultural shift into an organization with constructive dissatisfaction - you can put out a near perfect product and the feedback you’ll get is the delta from what you made, and perfection. This isn’t inherently a bad thing, and once you get used to it you can take it for what it is, which is just ways for you to improve.</p> <p>There’s this concept that once integrity is damaged it’s never recoverable, and that everyone has perfect, flawless integrity until the moment that they violate it - and then it’s gone forever. I’m going to borrow a wonderful quote and idea from a friend from a years ago that called integrity “the dress whites of the nuclear navy”. The expectation is absolute perfection, and it’s rarely attainable.</p> <p>So how do you reconcile those two concepts? The short answer is you don’t. There is a “right” way to do everything, and while some situations have more dire consequences than others, there’s this undercurrent in the culture that it doesn’t matter - everything must be done right. But everything also must be done on time, and under-budget. This creates a dichotomy of extremes where everyone is perfect and therefore every little mistake is blown out of the water.</p> <p>This is even more challenging in an organization with the word “nuclear” in front of it. Paradoxically I would say it’s also more challenging because we’re the largest nuclear organization in the world that has a flawless safety record. I remember when I was a student at the MARF prototype in upstate New York in 2017, we were doing field day to prepare for an upcoming inspection and some staff member was watching us clean and said something along the lines of:</p> <p>“You know, cleaning for inspections is a scam. You clean for days and days and theres only two outcomes.‘</p> <p>“One, the inspection team declares your boat clean. That means that the cleaning plan worked, and you should do the exact same thing next year to get the same grade.’</p> <p>“Two, the inspection team declares the boat unclean. This clearly means you didn’t clean enough, and next year you’ll just clean more. But you never clean less.”</p> <p>We have a clean boat. This means the cleaning plan worked, and we’ve done the exact same thing for the last 75 years to keep it clean. In all honesty, I don’t know the right answer. Is it because of the emphasis we place on integrity and the high standards we hold our sailors to? I don’t know, and it very well might be. Maybe it is the right answer to make a huge deal out of each small issue. It’s difficult to believe this, but it’s the thought process I believe a lot of people in this organization ascribe to.</p> <p>I don’t see integrity as this shining dress white uniform that gets stained permanently the moment it’s tarnished, but as a constant between 0 and 1 people check their actions against. And there’s so many ways that external forces can influence how high your constant needs to be to do the right thing. If you feel like your organization doesn’t care about you, it’ll tick up that integrity value you need to do the right thing. What about if you think your action is pointless? Tick it up. Don’t see a feasible way of accomplishing your job the right way on time? Tick it on up. What about feeling like you’ve already lost your integrity because of the shortcuts you’ve taken? Your constant is just going to go down.</p> <p>All of this is to illustrate the challenges of having people operate with integrity being a central tenet of their organization. Nobody comes to work or does a job with the plan of cutting corners. While this does not distract from the personal responsibility and liability of violating your integrity, it is incumbent on an organization to develop a culture that allows people to make mistakes and gives them a real opportunity to get their job done the right way. I’ve been in the Navy for almost 9 years and all of my adult life, and I have yet to see a situation where these testaments don’t hold true. Give people a real chance to do the right thing, and make them feel like they matter, and they almost always will.</p> <p>I have a strong memory of waking up to take the watch from another good friend of mine. I go down to relieve him, and he says,“Hey the meter isn’t working, so I just threw some numbers in. Control knows it broke, but I told them I fixed it.” I felt like Paul Atreides after he had ingested spice for the first time in the desert underneath a thin tent. I saw two terrible futures laid out before me, and the only right answer stood between them on a razors edge. I’m proud to say that I handled that situation with tact and technical acumen and got all technical issues resolved while informing the entire chain of command of the situation, and kept my friend his career. But I hated how it made me feel, and I hated the situation that forced me to feel that way.</p> <p>I have lies and cheats and scandals on my heart that are mine to bear until the day I die. I had impossible standards put forth before me and I met them at the expense of my soul. Does that absolve me of guilt? Absolutely not. Does that mean I lack integrity? I’m not sure, but I don’t think so.</p> <p>However, I will never put myself into a situation that will make me feel like that again. And because of this - and not a couple bucks - I will never re-enlist again in the navy.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-posts"/><category term="integrity"/><category term="navy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A rambling about integrity]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome!</title><link href="https://mshires.net//blog/2023/about/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome!"/><published>2023-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mshires.net//blog/2023/about</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mshires.net//blog/2023/about/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a test of the blogging system, and also a welcome to anyone interested in this site. Look around and feel free to reach out to me if you have any questions or just want to chat!</p> <p>This website is a fork of the <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">al-folio</a> that I’ve customized for my needs. It’s hosted by <a href="https://pages.github.com">GitHub Pages</a> at <a href="https://www.github.com/MichaelShires/MichaelShires.github.io/">my pages</a> repository, using <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com">Cloudflare</a> DNS provider.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-posts"/><category term="about"/><category term="michael"/><category term="first"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome!]]></summary></entry></feed>